<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to the booke called The perfect Pharisee under monkish holinesse: wherein is layd open, who they are that oppose the fundamentall principles of the doctrine of the Gospel, and the scripture practises, which the authors of that book would cast upon those they call Quakers, but are found to be themselves; who appear to be no ministers of the Gospel, but walke contrary to all that ever Christ sent forth in the scripture, scorning them who live the life of the scriptures, or are brought into the obedience of the same spirit. Published for no other end but to cleare the truth from the slanders of these men, who thereby goe about to deceive the simple, and keep them off from obedience to the truth. By one whom the world calls, James Nayler.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89827</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E735_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206955</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866037</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866037</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166904</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89827)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166904)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 113:E735[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to the booke called The perfect Pharisee under monkish holinesse: wherein is layd open, who they are that oppose the fundamentall principles of the doctrine of the Gospel, and the scripture practises, which the authors of that book would cast upon those they call Quakers, but are found to be themselves; who appear to be no ministers of the Gospel, but walke contrary to all that ever Christ sent forth in the scripture, scorning them who live the life of the scriptures, or are brought into the obedience of the same spirit. Published for no other end but to cleare the truth from the slanders of these men, who thereby goe about to deceive the simple, and keep them off from obedience to the truth. By one whom the world calls, James Nayler.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653 [i.e. 1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "may. 09. 1654.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Weld, Thomas, 1590?-1662. --  Perfect Pharisee under monkish holinesse --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166904:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Anſwer to the Booke called The perfect Phariſee UNDER MONKISH HOLINESSE: Wherein is layd open, who they are that oppoſe the Fundamentall Principles of the Doctrine of the Goſpel, and the Scripture pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, which the Authors of that Book would caſt upon thoſe they call <hi>Quakers,</hi> but are found to be themſelves; who appear to be no Miniſters of the Goſpel, but walke contrary to all that ever Chriſt ſent forth in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, ſcorning them who live the life of the Scriptures, or are brought into the obedience of the ſame ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for no other end, but to cleare the truth from the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of theſe men, who thereby goe about to deceive the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and keep them of from obedience to the truth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>They prepared a net for my ſteps my ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ule is b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wed downe, they have digged a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> before me into the midſt whereof they are fallen themſelves, Selah.</hi>
               </p> 
               <bibl>Pſal. 56. 7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By one whom the World calls, <hi>James Nayler.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:166904:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>FReind, There was a Booke lately ſet forth by five of the cheife Prieſts of the North, reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> who are all ſtrangers to that ſort of people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> except one; ſo thou may the rather perceive, what they have Written, is gathered by reports: which Booke, they cauſed to be diſperced and ſcattered abroad with much diligence. Thou wilt not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in this Anſwer finde any contention in the words of mans wiſedome, with what they call their confutation, but in plainneſſe and ſimplicity, what is truth, is owned; what is falſe, is denyed, and ſo much given forth to every thing, as may diſcover to him that hath the ſingle eye opened, by what ſpirit theſe men are ſeverally acted. Reade with underſtanding, and minde not the multitude of words, leaſt thou be deceived; Truth needs no covers.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166904:2"/>
            <p>NOw that the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is appearing in his Saints to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcover the man of ſinne with all his dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts and deceiveable workings, as is foretold in the Scriptures; Now all the powers of darkeneſſe are gathering together againſt him. <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> whoſe number is as the ſana of the Sea for multitude; but it is, that the Scripture of truth may be fulfiled according to the Prophets, concerning theſe Heathen, who know nothing of God, and Chriſt, and their raging imaginations againſt the Kingdome of the holy one. And as it was at his appearance upon earth formerly, <hi>Herod, and all Jeruſalem was moved;</hi> neither could that ſpirit of envie that was in them ever be at reſt, till they had accompliſhed their end, that was to take away his life. And as then the chiefe Prieſts, <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilat,</hi> who never loved one another, nor could agree in any other thing; yet in this they were all agreed, to take part againſt the Lambe. And it is the ſame at this day with the ſame ſeed, as plainely appears with theſe five, with many more, who formerly could ſcarce agree in any thing, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o not in that which they call, The worſhip of God,</hi> but have been at jarres and diſputes among themſelves, one contending for one way, another for another; yet now in this they are all one, and their conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ltations againſt the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e where he is manifeſt, inventing lyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſeeking for falſe witneſſe againſt them in whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e is, as will appeare in this their Booke; and rendring them, and what they doe in obedience to God, under the name of <hi>Monkiſh holineſſe, Fryars, Phariſees,</hi> or any thing that in their ſubtilty they conceive will make them moſt odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to people who know not their converſation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and leaſt any who ſee their conve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſation ſhould be convinced<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by their w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lking in ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dience to Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt they are not afr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d to ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> evill of their forſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>king the World the pride and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſts of it the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommands of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and without which, none <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n come unto him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and theſe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll, <hi>ſinfull neg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll obſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rvati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi> and belyes the Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, ſaying th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>the rudimen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166904:3"/>
the world,</hi> as though the Apoſtle was ſet to diſanull the commands of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>He that will be my Diſciple muſt forſake the world, and what is deare in it; yea to wife and children houſe and land, for none can ſerve God and Mammon:</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat thoſe whom they would reproach doe in obedience to Chriſt and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, they call ſhewes, and will worſhips or any thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe to make them odious; but all who are guided by the ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it of light, may pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inely ſee by what ſpirit theſe men are acted, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eud all their ſubtilty, that they may ſtrike at the Kingdome of Chriſt in his owne, whereby he brings forth obedience in them to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and whereby they are brought to follow him who was not of this world, nor did live in the delights of it, nor had whereon to lay his head; but were hated, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elyed, and perſecuted by thoſe Prieſts and people, that lived in pride and fulneſſe and the holly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gods of this world as theſe who follow him are by the ſame gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration at this day: but as then, he that was borne after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was borne after the ſpirit even ſo it is now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but it is, that the Scriptures may be fulfilled and the power of the Almighty ſeen in carrying on hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re deſpiſed little Flocke, againſt all the rage of the Heathen that know him not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor his power; and hereby will he get himſelfe a name, and herein do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we rejoyee, yea and ſhall rejoy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e for ever.</p>
            <p>FOr that you call the firſt Poſition that is, That <hi>George Fox</hi> ſhould ſay, <hi>He was equall with God</hi> I anſwer, That he did ſay that <hi>George Fox</hi> was equall with God, is falſe; for I was in the hearing before ſome juſtices of the Peace, when he was asked <hi>Whether he ſpake true of</hi> George Fox <hi>as he was a creature?</hi> To which he anſwered, <hi>I deny</hi> George Fox, <hi>he is duſt, and muſt to duſt; but I and my Father are one; and he that is joyned to the Lord is one ſpirit, and ſo the Scripture ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but they that are in the fleſh cannot witneſſe it.</hi> At which the Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were ſatisfied that he ſpake of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pirit of Chriſt in him, and thereupon they did acquit him. It is true That <hi>Marſhall</hi> did ſweare at <hi>Apleby,</hi> and the other; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when he came to ſpeak of <hi>George Fox</hi> being equall with God; one of the Juſtices <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there upon the Bench, who was preſent at <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſter</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en <hi>George Fox</hi> ſpake the words; did openly witneſſe again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalls</hi> falſe Oath in the hearing of the open <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:166904:3"/>To your ſecond untruth, that <hi>Iames Nayler</hi> ſhould ſay, <hi>That he was as holy, juſt and good as God.</hi> I anſwer, that holineſſe, juſtneſſe and goodneſſe that I witneſſe, is no other, but the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, juſtneſſe, and goodneſſe of God himſelfe, in the Face of Ieſus Chriſt: for all my owne holineſſe, juſtneſſe, and goodneſſe I doe deny; but that ever I did ſay, that I was as holy, juſt, and good as God, is an untruth, and was never ſpoken by me, nor ever did it enter into my thoughts, but is a lye rayſed up by the Father of lyes the Devill, and vented by his ſervants to make the truth odious: And the Lord God of truth, before whom I ſtand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> judge between me and you in this thing; for you are of that generation who ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Come, let us deviſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 18. 18. &amp; 20. 10.</note> 
               <hi>againſt him; come, let us ſmite him with the Tongue; report, ſay they, and we will report it:</hi> but the Lord will deliver his truth out of your hands. And for <hi>William Baldwinſon,</hi> whom you father this untruth on, I never had any private diſcourſe with him, nor ever was I in company where he was, but once in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arrow,</hi> where was the houſe full of people that I had never ſeen before; and if he ſhould affirme any ſuch thing, they of his owne Towne ſhall all witneſſe againſt him; but I ſtand to the witneſſe of God. Nor, as it falls on my ſelfe, ſhould I have mentioned it; but as it falls on the truth, and may offend ſome weake ones who is more to me then all outward reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the World.</p>
            <p>To your third, <hi>That</hi> George Fox <hi>did affirme, that he was the Iudre of the World; And that one wrote from</hi> Carlile, <hi>that called</hi> George Fox, <hi>the Sonne of God.</hi> I anſwer, you here ſhew your ſelves to be ignorant of Chriſt ſpiritually borne up in you, who is the Iudge of the world in whom he is, which the Saints did witneſſe, as it is p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aine in the Scriptures, <hi>Know you not that</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Saints ſhall Iudge the World? Yea, Angels and the ſpirituall man judgeth all things,</hi> yet he himſelfe is judged of no man. Now you that have not this infallible ſpirit to judge with, have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe to judge of the things of God, but are carnall and naturall, and judge with evill thoughts, and call evill good, and good evill; for the naturall man receives not the things of the ſpirit of God, and what you know naturally as bruite beaſts, therein you corrupt your ſelves; and you that are offended
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166904:4"/>
that one ſhall witneſſe the Sonne of God, ſhew that you are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the New Birth, which whoſoever witneſſes is the Sonne of God: yea, you are ignorant of the Scriptures, which ſaith, <hi>Behold with what manner of love the Father loved us, that</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>we ſhould be called the Sons of God;</hi> and we are Sons already, and it doth not yet appeare what we ſhall be. Now bluſh for ſhame that you ſhould be Miniſters of the letter, and are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant of it, and would ſlander them that owne it.</p>
            <p>Now for your confuſed confutation of the lyes you have ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt us, I ſhall ſay nothing to them.</p>
            <p>For that you call your ſecond Poſition, <hi>That there is no diſtinction of Perſons in the God head</hi> This you ſay <hi>George Fox</hi> layes downe in <hi>Saul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> errand to Damaſcus, pag.</hi> 12. Now all may take notice if theſe men regard what they ſpeake or write, ſo that they can but make th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truth odious to others, when they are not aſhamed to Print ſo plaine an untruth, that is ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that all that ever read that page in <hi>Sauls errand,</hi> may wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt them that the words they have ſet downe are not there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but they have gathered them up in their inventions, wherewith they imagine lyes againſt the innocent; and to caſt upon the truth; neither have they any proofe for what they here accuſe of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>For your third Poſition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſoule is a part of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce.</hi> And this you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you had from Collonell <hi>Benſon</hi> and Captain <hi>Ward<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is you know not who live in the fall, and are v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne contenders and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaders for ſin, which keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at a di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance from God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and while you are ſervants of ſinne, your ſoules are in death; but the firſt man <hi>Adam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> was a living ſoule; the ſecond a quickning ſpirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and he that is joyned to the Lord is one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And this we wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and all witneſſe it who are come up o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of the fall: but you who live in diſobedience, acting thoſe things which Chriſt forbad, knowes nothing of the living ſoule; for you watch not for the good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſoules, for you ſeek for your gaine from your Quarter and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>kes peoples money for that which is not Bread, and all who fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> are unſatisfied: but all you who hearken di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to the voyce of the Lord, their ſoules doe live, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Lord, and are united to him, and he that is not, is againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:166904:4"/>For your fourth Poſition, <hi>That Chriſt is in every man, and in the reprobate he is held under corruption;</hi> and this you ſay, one of you received from <hi>Iames Nayler</hi> in conference with him, <hi>wherein he extended the in-dwelling of Chriſt to Indians that never heard the Goſpel.</hi> I anſwer When will you ceaſe to adde your lyes to ſlander withall? That which I held forth was that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was the light of the world, and lighteneth every one that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into the world; which <hi>William Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> denyed: I bad him put out one amongſt all that great multitude that durſt deny it. He ſaid, thoſe were <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and had heard the Goſpel, but <hi>Indians</hi> had not that light. I told him, he went far for a proofe, but if an <hi>Indian</hi> were there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he would witneſſe againſt him. But O thou full of all ſubtilty. Did I ſay, <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Chriſt in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates is held under corruption?</hi> let all that was there be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt thee. Now that <hi>Chriſt</hi> enlightens every one that comes into the world, is plaine <hi>Scripture;</hi> and if <hi>Chriſt</hi> be not in the moſt vile in the world, there to ſee the heart, thoughts, and intents, how ſhall he judge every one according to their thoughts that come not forth into actions, as well as according to what they doe? muſt he then proceed as carnall Iudges doe, either by proofe or confeſſion, and no further? and muſt not he judge <hi>Indians,</hi> as well as others? and who ſhall tell him what is in their hearts and thoughts? Here you ſhew your ſelves igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of that <hi>Chriſt</hi> who is ſpirituall, and judgeth not after the outward appearance, but is all, and in all; and are of the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome others of you, who ſay, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is in Heaven with a carnall body; but here is your folly manifeſt to all the Children of light.</p>
            <p>And whereas you accuſe <hi>Iohn Audland</hi> for writing to <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ggs,</hi> and telling him, <hi>That he who once had been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, and departed out of it, did crucifie Ieſus Chriſt within him.</hi> I anſwer, Reade <hi>Hebrews</hi> 6. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. and ſee if the Apoſtle ſpeake not the ſame words, ſaying <hi>That ſuch crucifie the Lord of life afreſh, and put him to open ſhame.</hi> And that it is ſuch a haynous thing to you (who knowes not Chriſt in you) for any to ſay, that Chriſt is in them: Was it not Ieſus of <hi>Naz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reth</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> perſecuted, when he hayled the Saints to Priſon? <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 4. 5. and was not Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the Saints, the hope of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166904:5"/>
glory, and all this after his Aſſention? But you who cannot witneſſe his ſecond appearing without ſin unto ſalvation, are ignorant of this, and therefore perſecute him where he is.</p>
            <p>For your fifth Poſition, <hi>That Chriſt in the fleſh, with all he did and ſuffered therein, was but a figure, and nothing but an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> and this you ſay is expreſſely found in their Booke called <hi>Sauls Errand to Damaſcus,</hi> pag. 8. 3. I anſwer, we doe owne and confeſſe, that Ieſus Chriſt in the fleſh is a figure or exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to us to follow, till we come up to his fulneſſe and meaſure, as the Saints in Scripture doe witneſſe. But O deceitfull ſpirits,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13. 15.</note> is this to ſay, that all that Chriſt did and ſuffered in the fleſh, was but a figure, and nothing but an example; or is the words<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 1.</note> expreſſely ſound in <hi>Sauls Errand,</hi> as you ſay they are, let that Booke be witneſſe againſt you, and your lying ſlanders herein to all that reade it: And you ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that this was written in a Letter which <hi>Nayler</hi> wrote to one in <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> viz. <hi>That he that expects to be ſaved by him that dyed at Ieruſalem ſhould be deceived;</hi> which is a moſt filthy untruth: and I challenge all the generation of ſlanderers to produce any ſuch Letter under my hand, or any ſuch thing from my mouth; for I owne no other Chriſt, but that which ſuffered at Ieruſalem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by him I am ſaved from my ſins; but had I not knowne him in me, my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer and Hope of glory, I had not known him at Ieruſalem; nor ſhould I have had any more benefit by him, then covetous proud lyars, ſlanderers, envyers, and ſuch like, who ſhall not enter into the Kingdome of Heaven though they talke of what he did at Ieruſalem; and yet live in their ſinnes and filthineſſe. And all that have eyes may ſee how you invent your lyes, and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13. 15.</note> caſt them upon us; and then, in that you call your con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utations, adde your owne imaginations to them, to make us odious to all; As becauſe we ſay, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is our example, therefore the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary</hi> muſt be in us and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in us, and <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the eleven Apoſtles, <hi>Iudas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Herod<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>Pilat</hi> in us, and much ſuch like ſtuffe which I ſhall not now mention, but leave it to any, where there is an honeſt principle of light to judge, by what ſpirit theſe men are acted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and how groundleſſe theſe ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are they caſt upon us.</p>
            <p>For your ſixth Poſition, <hi>that men are not juſtified by the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166904:5"/>
of Chriſt which he in his owne Perſon did fulfill without us.</hi> I anſwer, what righteouſneſſe Chriſt hath performed without me, was not my juſtification, neither was I ſaved by it, but was ſtill in my ſins, and a ſervant to ſin, untill Chriſt appeared in me, who is my life, and by faith in him, gave me victory over my ſins, and led captivitie captive in me, and brought forth judgement into victory in me and appeared in me my righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, juſtification, and redemption, and ſo in me the hope of glory; till which time, all my Prayers, Teares and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, could not produce an everlaſting peace, but ſtill was overpowred by the powers of ſin, though I could talke of Faith and Redemption, yet I had not the witneſſe within my ſelfe, which witneſse is Chriſt Jeſus. And you that talke of a Faith, and what Chriſt did at Jeruſalem, and cannot witneſse the ſame Chriſt in you, to Redeeme you, but are ſtill in your ſins, led <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> by your luſts into pride, and covetouſneſse, envy, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ckbiting, and ſuch like filthineſse: Why hath not drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, ſwearers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſuch like, as are captivated by thoſe ſins, as muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght to what Chriſt ſuffered at Jeruſalem, as you, ſeeing they wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, they beleeve in him, that he dyed for them, as wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as you though both live in your ſins, and ſo count the Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od of Chriſt an unholy thing?</p>
            <p>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your ſeventh Poſition, <hi>that men are juſtified by that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe which Chriſt within us enables us to performe, or</hi> (which is in effect, and ſome of them have expreſsed, by inherent righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſse) <hi>and you ſay it is affirmed by</hi> Iames Nayler <hi>in a Book, wherein it is ſaid, this light within you will let you ſee your ſins, bring to repentance and tenderneſſe of heart, bring you to feare God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo leade up to juſtification and peace.</hi> I anſwer, How the holding for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h that the light of Chriſt leades up to theſe<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 12.</note> things (which the Scriptures doe witneſse) doth hold forth an inherent righteouſneſse<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let any wiſe man judge; but by wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truth to ſlander<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you would deceive the ſimple. And you ſay, <hi>Nayler</hi> ſaith, <hi>We are not reconciled to God, till we be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy, and able to ſtand ſo in our owne power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> pag. 25. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that no unperfect thing can be reconciled to God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is plain in Scripture: but that I ſaid or writ. That man muſt be able to ſtand in his owne power, is an horrid lye, as the Boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166904:6"/>
witneſſe againſt you, wherein is Printed quite contrary; and leaſt any ſhould not have the Booke, and ſo beleeve this falſe ſlander, I ſhall ſet downe the words as they are Printed <hi>pag.</hi> 25. the words of the Quaere are theſe, <hi>Whether God created man and woman perfect, without ſinne, and able in his own power to have ſtood, if they had not forſaken his power, and conſented to the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Serpent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea, or no?</hi> Now what truth is in theſe men, who notwithſtanding the word be twice over repeated, <hi>to ſtand in Gods power;</hi> yet they are not aſhamed to wreſt it to their own power: but what is in their hearts, may appeare to all men by this, as in the reſt of the untruths in their Booke, which are not a few. And to your Poſition <hi>of being juſtified by any of our own workings,</hi> we deny; for it is he that worketh in us to will and to doe of his good pleaſure; and herein we deny ſelfe works, and ſelfe will, and ſtand in the will and workings of another, bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <p>For your eight Poſition, <hi>That God and Man cannot be wholly reconciled, till he be brought into the ſtate of the firſt</hi> Adam, <hi>and able in his own power to ſtand perfect.</hi> And for proofe of this, you refer the Reader to a Booke of <hi>Naylers,</hi> pag. 26. And you ſay, <hi>that their owne eyes may ſatisfie them there.</hi> I anſwer, That the Reader may be ſatisfied in the truth of what you ſay, I ſhall ſet downe the plaine words in <hi>pag.</hi> 26. and the words of the Quaere are theſe, <hi>Whether God and Man be wholly reconciled, till Man be brought into that eſtate againe, yea, or no?</hi> Now that God and Man is not reconciled till he be redeemed, is plaine in Scripture; but that here is any thing in theſe words ſpoken by me, <hi>of Man being able in his owne power to ſtand,</hi> let the Reader judge, who may plainly ſee, how you adde to my words, your owne inventions to ſlander withall, which are neither ſpoken, not thought by me; for I ſpoke of <hi>Adam</hi> being able to have ſtood in Gods power, if he had not forſaken his power, and conſented to the wiſedome of the Serpent, which you wreſt, <hi>to his owne power;</hi> but wickedneſſe ſhall be on the head of the wicked. And you that ſay, That <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was under the covenant of works, make it appear to all that know <hi>Adams</hi> ſtate, that you never knew it; for the Law, wherein is the covenant of works, was added after, becauſe of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166904:6"/>
the tranſgreſſion, but being ignorant of the ſpirit by which theſe things are known, you imagine of them in your carnall wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and as your Books leade you; but <hi>Adams</hi> innocent eſtate you knew not.</p>
            <p>For your ninth Poſition, <hi>that no man that commits ſinne, or that is not perfectly holy, can ever enter into the Kingdome of Heaven, unleſſe there be a Purgatory.</hi> And you ſay, <hi>James Nayler</hi> in his Booke before quoted, <hi>pag. 26. puts it by way of quaerie.</hi> I anſwer; in <hi>pag.</hi> 26. there is not a word to that purpoſe as you have ſet downe; but ſeeing you are miſtaken in this, as in many more things, I ſhall help your miſtake, for the better informing of the Reader: in pag. 25. (which you intend) the words of the quaere are theſe, <hi>Whether any unperfect and uncleane one that lives in ſin, ſhall enter into the Kingdome of Heaven, yea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or zo? And if not, how ſhall one dying in ſinne? and where ſhall he be made perfect and cleane, ſeeing the tree muſt lye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s it falls? and whether you own a Purgatory, yea, or no?</hi> Now I ſhall appear to any one that is gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a Principle of truth, whether you have not wreſted my words quite to another ſence? as though I ſaid, no man that hath ſinned, can ever enter into the Kingdome; and as though I owned a Purgatory: but you are ſo uſed to wreſt the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures (being unlearned) and ſo uſed to turne the truth into a lye by your ſerpents wiſedome, that you cannot ceaſe from it; and were it not, that what is Printed that cannot be altered, did witneſſe againſt you, it would not be beleeved that ſuch as you profeſſe your ſelves to be, ſhould ſo wholly give your ſelves to ſerve the Father of lyes: but bleſſed be God, who is laying open your deceipt, whereby you have deſtroyed ſoules, and in the pit you have digged<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you ſhall be taken, but the ſimple ſhall eſcape your ſnares. You ſay, The blood of Chriſt is your Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, which cleanſeth the ſoule from all ſins, yet as to perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall actings very guilty; and to prove it, you quote 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 7. but doth that Text ſay, any are cleanſed from ſin, while they perſonally act ſin? or the quite contrary; who ſaith, <hi>If we walk in the light, as he is in the light, we have fellowſhip one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and the blood of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>his Sonne, cleanſeth us from all ſinne.</hi> Now, he that <hi>walks</hi> in the light doth not commit ſin, for ſin is darkeneſſe; but you that <hi>talke</hi> of being cleanſed by the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:166904:7"/>
blood of Chriſt, and yet live in ſin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> counts the blood of Chriſt an unholy thing; but you muſt pleade for your Fathers King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and you are faithfull to him, as appears in all this your Booke.</p>
            <p>For your tenth Poſition, <hi>No reall Saint but he that is perfect, and perfectly holy in this life, and doth not ſin.</hi> And you ſay, <hi>it is</hi> Naylers <hi>deſigne in his Booke to prove this,</hi> pag. 21. 22. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, It ſeems there can be no greater offence with you, then<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 8.</note> to cry downe ſin, and to grow up to perfection, though it is the very end for which Chriſt is manifeſt, <hi>viz.</hi> To deſtroy the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 28.</note> works of the Devill, and to preſent the Saints perfect to the Father, as is plaine in Scripture. And here you ſhew what Kingdome you are of, who pleade ſo much againſt the end of Chriſts comming. And in your 11. page, you quote <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 10. and ſaith, there the Apoſtle clearely holds forth an univerſall impoſſibility to fulfill the righteouſneſſe of the Law, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Not one jot ſhall fall till all be fulfilled.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 3. 4. That God ſent his owne Sonne, that the righteouſneſſe of the Law might be fulfilled in us, who walke not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit: And here you bely the Apoſtle, and deny the end of <hi>Chriſts</hi> comming, and pleade for continuing in ſin and imperfection, as is plaine in this you call your confutation, wherein you wreſt and twine the Scriptures, to pleade for the Devills Kingdome, and putting cleanſing from ſin and perfection afar off<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> till after death in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, and all to make the commands of God, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the Saints, and comming of Chriſt, of no effect here, but all muſt ſerve ſin here: and you ſet it downe as a ſtrange thing, that <hi>Richard Farneſworth</hi> ſhould ſay, That no uncleane thing can enter into the Kingdome of Heaven, though it be plaine Scripture; but you muſt appeare, for now God is ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the pretious from the vile, the day is come.</p>
            <p>For your eleventh Poſition, <hi>that every man in the world hath a light within him ſufficient to guide him to ſalvation, without the helpe of any outward light or diſcovery.</hi> I anſwer, That <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> is the onely light, and there is none beſides him to guide to ſalvation, and that he is the light of the whole world, and was given of the Father for that end, is plaine in the whole
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166904:7"/>
Scriptures: The Prophets propheſied of him, That he ſhould be given for a light, even to the Gentiles. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> beares<note place="margin">Iſay 42 6.</note> witneſſe, That he was not that light, but came to beare witneſſe to it; and that was the true light that lightneth every one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that commeth into the world. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8. 9. Chriſt ſaith of himſelfe, I am the light of the world he that follows me ſhall not walke in darkeneſſe, but ſhall have the light of life. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 12. Again, This is the condemnation, that light is come into the world, and men love darkeneſſe rather then light, becauſe their deeds are evill. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 19. Now this light ſhines in darkeneſſe, but<note place="margin">Iohn 1. 4. 5.</note> the darkeneſſe comprehends it not; and here are you, who calls this light a naturall light, and denyes the words of Chriſt and the Prophets, and would make them lyars like you, and all the world ſhall witneſſe againſt you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they have a light that lets them ſee when they ſinne, which if they did minde and obey, woule leade out of ſin to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and all who have obeyed it, ſhall witneſſe it, and this light of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is perfect in its mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as it ariſeth, and needs no outward light or diſcovery: And this is the cauſe why this light is ſo hated of the Devill, and them that love their ſins, becauſe the Devill can have no hold in any corner of the heart, but this will diſcover him; and no ſinne can be committed, but it checks for it, till the candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke be removed by often ſinning againſt it, for the light of the wicked ſhall be put out; and this is that light which teſtifies of Jeſus, and the teſtimony of Jeſus is the ſpirit of Propheſie, and it is that more ſure word of propheſie and light that ſhines in a darke place, and leads to the day-ſtar ſpoken of in 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 1. 19. to which he exhorts all to take heed, though ye children of darkeneſſe cannot comprehend it, and therefore deny it, and tells people that we meane of the principles left in man ſince the fall, and that we deny the Fountaine of living waters, and goe not to <hi>Ieſus</hi> for light; and ſo by giving your falſe meanings upon our writings, as you doe upon the Scriptures, you caſt lyes upon the truth, and calls this light of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> a naturall light; and here you deny the Fountaine of light, and would put it out, that you might live in your deeds of darkeneſſe undiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, as doth appear by all your twyning and cunning wynding and lying in that which you call confutation; but who are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166904:8"/>
guided by the true light, may eaſily judge of your confuſed ſtuffe, which I forbeare, as not worth naming.</p>
            <p>For your twelfth Poſition, <hi>that there is no need of any outward teaching by reading or hearing the Scriptures opened and applyed.</hi> I<note place="margin">
                  <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> 31. 31. 32 33. 34.</note> anſwer, The promiſe of the new covenant is, That all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Lord, ſhall be taught of the Lord; and they ſhall<note place="margin">Heb. 8. 10. 11.</note> not need that any teach his neighbour, ſaying, Know the Lord, for all ſhall know him by his own teaching, from the greateſt to the leaſt of them: And for this end is Chriſt the light of the world, the Shepheard and Biſhop of ſoules: and when he came, he denyed all the hireling teachers, and ſaid, they have nought to doe with the ſheep, for his ſheep heare his voyce, and will not follow the voyce of a ſtranger; and he who knowes this teacher<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> knowes him to be a ſufficient teacher alone, For who teache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> like him who gives to every one ſeaſonable food? That <hi>Iohn Aud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſaid No need of outward teaching, is falſe; the word was, He needed no man to teach him, the Lord was his teacher: But you who know not this teacher, apply the Scriptures to all hand over head, and give the promiſes that is to the ſeed of God, which ſeed is but one, and is pure, and theſe promiſes you give to them who are in the firſt birth ſtill in their ſins and ſo doubt with untempered morter, and ſowes pillowes under every arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hole, ſo that none turnes from their ſins, for you preach them up all beleevers, except ſome that refuſe to give you hire, and them you prepare war againſt. And whereas you alledge, the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtles; it is true, they in whom Chriſt was riſen, the light, and life, and teacher, they went out and Preached the Reſurrection to others, to gather all to this Teacher, and told them, that Chriſt was their light and life, and exhorted them to waite for his appearance in them, and that as he appeared, their life ſhould appeare with him; and when they had directed them where to waite for teaching, and gathered them out of the teachings of the hirelings, they left them, and went on to call more out of the world to this teacher, and appointed the ſtrong who were come to the teachings of Chriſt, to take the overſight of the weake, leaſt there ſhould be a turning through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of the falſe teachers and hirelings, before they came to ſee the teachings of Chriſt, and his appearing; and ſuch was not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166904:8"/>
to keep a talking to them for filthy lucre, but to watch over them of a ready minde; neither did they take a verſe of another mans condition, and ſay to them, Heare the Word of the Lord, when the Lord had not ſpoken it to them, but what was moved to be written to them by the holy Ghoſt, was read to them without adding or diminiſhing; and the ſame ſpirit hath the ſame workings now, where it is in its meaſure, which brings all things to our remembrance according to his mighty work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in us. And whereas you ſay that <hi>George Fox</hi> pretended to <hi>have all from within; yet his jugling was diſcovered, a Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance being ſent to him to help his memory.</hi> I anſwer. What the ſpirit did teach the Saints, it doth teach them the ſame now within; but the Scripture was not put in Chapter and Verſe by the ſpirit, but the hireling Prieſts have done it to trade withall; and though for his owne teachings within he need no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward help; yet having to doe with quoting Verſes, which was not by the ſpirit, but in the invention, he might uſe a Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, not at all to adde to himſelfe, but to quote Scriptures to convince others. And Scripture was uſed by Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, to convince gaine-ſayers, though they needed not uſe them in regard of themſelves, but had the ſame ſpirit that gave them forth, and was taught by it, and not by the letter. And whereas you tell of your Miniſtry having undenyable ſeales of your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration in the witnes of Chriſt therto, begetting many ſoules to converſion. I anſwer, The witneſſe of Chriſt is againſt you and your Miniſtry, who came to ſet free from ſin; but you ſay, men muſt commit ſin while they live, and be ſet free when they are dead. <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that commits ſinne is the ſervant of ſinne,</hi> and ſuch are you and your converts.</p>
            <p>For your thirteenth Poſition, <hi>That the Scriptures are not the Word of God, but a Declaration of the conditions of them that ſpoke them forth. I</hi> anſwer, The Scripture ſaith, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the word by whom all things were made was before all time, which Word became fleſh and dwelt in the Saints. Now if the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures be the Word which had their beginning ſince all were made, and did not become fleſh, then there is two Words of God. Now prove that in Scripture, or that the Letter is called the Word in plaine words, and the Apoſtle calls what he wro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166904:9"/>
a Declaration. 1 <hi>Iohn 1. 1. 2. 3. The things that we have heard and ſeen, declare we unto you.</hi> Now who denyes the Scriptures, whether we that ſpeake the plaine words as they are, or you that deny them, and would have us to beleeve your meanings and wreſtings of them, when you have no plain Scripture for what you ſay? And whereas you ſay, it cannot be underſtood to be the Word <hi>Chriſt</hi> that came to the Prophets, <hi>Samuel, Jeremy, &amp;c.</hi> where it ſeems your underſtanding is not that with the Apoſtle, who ſaith, <hi>it was the ſpirit of Chriſt that was in them,</hi> 1 Pet. 1 11. but all your wreſtings will not cover your folly. And you ſay, what <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles Preached, Spoke or Wrote, was not <hi>Chriſt, the Father, or Spirit;</hi> when as the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſaith, That <hi>holy men of God ſpoke as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 21. And you ſay, to ſay <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the Word, is to deſtroy the Foundation of Faith, to make the Scriptures loſe their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; and diverſe ſuch like falſe concluſions. <hi>I</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to build all upon him in whom all is fulfilled, is to eſtabliſh Faith and Scripture, and all where it muſt ſtand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as on the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the authority of all Scriptures, and not the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and in him they are all profitable, and not elſe.</p>
            <p>For your fourteenth Poſition, <hi>that the ſpirits are not to be tryed by the Scripture.</hi> I anſwer, The infallible ſpirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is the Originall of all Scriptures is the try<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll of all ſpirits, and that ſpirituall man judgeth all things, and by that ſpirit, the ſaints was to judge of all ſpirits<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and gave thoſe up to <hi>Sathan</hi> that was for that end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as is p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aine, 1 <hi>Corinth</hi> 5. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And by this ſpirit was the ſpirits tryed before the letter w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; and all that are guided by the ſpirit of God, are the ſons of God, and are one, and in one minde, and have one rule, and one Faith,; but you who have no guide but the Letter, How many minds, how many formes, how many gods doe you worſhip? and all pretend <hi>Scripture,</hi> one wreſting it one way; another, another way: But what true tryall of ſpirits can you have here? For you five, though one ſpirit act you al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt the truth; yet you have your ſeverall wayes, formes, worſhips and ſpirits, and all pretend <hi>Scriptures:</hi> but who hath that true ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of judgement, is able to try you all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſees you all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out: and whereas you quote that place, <hi>To the Law and to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:166904:9"/>
teſtimony;</hi> it is true, The Law of the new covenant is written in the heart by God; and the Teſtimony of Jeſus, is the ſpirit of propheſie; and if any be not guided by, and ſpeake according to theſe, it is becauſe they have not the light in them, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them; and here you are whoſe light is without you, and therefore it is that you ſpeake contrary to them who ſpeake from the true light in them, even the witneſſe in themſelves. Now all your falſe concluſions, (as, that to be guided by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is to draw the ſoule from the judgement of God) and you citing <hi>Iohn Gilpin</hi> againſt the truth; it is no more then if the chiefe Prieſts ſhould have cited <hi>Iudas</hi> to have confuted Chriſt, and the reſt of the eleven Apoſtles, which truth they owned and ſuffered for, though he denyed it, and conſulted with the Prieſts to betray it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as <hi>Iohn Gilpin</hi> hath done now, who ſhall receive his reward, and you Prieſts alſo.</p>
            <p>For your fifteenth Poſition, <hi>That there ought to be no ſenſe, meaning, or expoſition given, or ſtudying of the Scriptures.</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, What hath been ſaid before, may ſuffice as to this, onely the ſpirit gave out the Scriptures, either perfect, or not perfect: If perfect, then let them alone as they are, and doe not darken them by your invented wiſedome, that they may be read and fulfilled in the Saints; for that is the end for which they were given forth, Not to trade with for Tythes and Money; and here the practice of all the Saints ſhall witneſſe againſt you, for they were ſpoken by the holy men of God, as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt; and they were written to ſuch as were come out of the world, pride, envie, and covetouſneſſe. Now you that live in thoſe ſins and filthy luſts, and are of the world, have nothing in them but your judgements that is to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed upon you from the wrath of the Almighty: and you that wreſt them, to pleade for ſin, are raized out of them, for they were given to warue off ſin: and you that have not that infallible ſpirit that gave them forth, what will you judge, and open, and expound them with, for the ſerpents<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wiſedome is ſhut out of them, and can doe nought, but twine and wreſt them to their owne deſtruction and keeping poore ſoules that beleeve you, in ſin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the fall, who cannot witneſſe their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and freedome from ſin, but are fed with words, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:166904:10"/>
profeſſion without life and power, or hopes ever to have power while they live. And though you alledge diverſe which you ſay expounded, yet not one of them will warrant your way of trading, nor your covetous practiſes.</p>
            <p>For your ſixteenth Poſition, <hi>They cry downe Baptiſme with Water, and the Lords Supper, as being but types and ſhadows, cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon the appearance of Chriſt within them.</hi> I anſwer, You your ſelves doe not ſay that they are the ſpirituall ſubſtance; but as for your Baptizing Infants, it is a meere invention, and hath no ground in Scripture, and we deny it: but if any one out of a tender conſcience doe obſerve it, as ſeeking to fulfill any command, as he conceives, I ſhall not judge him that is weake; onely, if ſuch a one reſt there, and come not to the Baptiſme of Chriſt, which is with fire and the ſpirit, Water-Baptiſme will not profit him: and he that once raſtes of the ſubſtance, will not goe backe to the ſhadow. And <hi>Paul</hi> knew what he ſpoke, when he thanked God that he had Baptized no more, for Chriſt (ſaith he) ſent me not to <hi>Baptize,</hi> but to <hi>Preach.</hi> And for the outward ſignes of the <hi>Supper, Doe this in remembrance of me till I come;</hi> but when he was come, then the bread which they did breake was the body of Chriſt, they being many were one bread, which whoever comes to witneſſe in ſpirit, will both ſee and ſay, That your Bread and Wine is carnall, and not ſpirituall: and your way of giving it without ground and life who are not one bread, nor of one heart and ſoule, as all are who breake this Bread of life: but they who reſt in the types<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> come ſhort of the ſubſtance, as is plain in your diviſions and contentions. Circumciſion was a true command of God; but who once witneſſed the circumciſion within of the heart, denyed that without; and then they who was igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of that was within, ſtood in the Figure, and perſecuted him who had the ſubſtance: and ſo it is now.</p>
            <p>For your ſeventeenth Poſition, <hi>That there is no mediate call to the Miniſtry.</hi> I anſwer, Where in Scripture will you prove a call to the Miniſtry by Man, Magiſtrates, Townes, or Pariſhes, or from one people to another, there to reſt and live in pride and idleneſſe, and the people to maintaine you by their labours, and you to live idle, and to be a Maſter over them? but thoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:166904:10"/>
who were ſent to Preach the Goſpel, denyes that they were made Miniſters by the will of man, and had no certaine dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place, but went up and downe in the world Preaching the Word, and diſputing in the Synagogues with them that held up the Idol worſhip, though they ſuffered for it where ever they came. And when they had gathered Churches out of the world, they did not bid them hyre a man to talke to them for money; but ordayned them Elders of themſelves, which were to take care of the weake freely, and not to runne from place to place for money, as you Prieſts doe; and theſe were ordayned not by man, but by ſuch as did it by the direction of the ſpirit of God; for they who ordayned them had the gift of the ſpirit, which they received of them; and this ordination was not by man, nor by the Churches, but by the power of God, and his ſpirit, in whom it was, and they had the giſt of the holy Ghoſt from their hands. Now what is this to your Parſonage, or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh callings; for ſhame take not this for a ſhelter for your co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous practice, and being ſet in great Livings by club Law, or the power of the Magiſtrate; for this practice of the Saints condemnes, you and your callings, and whole practice. Nor is here any ground at all for your bargaining with the people, or any ſet maintenance, or to ſue your hearers at Law for carnall things, or take their goods by violence; for ſhame, take not the <hi>Scriptures</hi> which witneſſe againſt your oppreſſion, and pride, and covetouſneſſe, nor the practice of the holy men of God, to prove your filthy practice, who hated the leaſt appearance of ſuch things, and could not endure that covetouſneſſe ſhould be ſo much as named amongſt them: For ſhame ceaſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the truth by your corrupt minds, and turning it into a lye, for your ſelfe ends<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Repent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the plagues of God are upon ſuch practice, and ceaſe to deceive ſoules for gaine, the Lord is ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to lay you open, and is comming with ten thouſand of his Saints to be avenged of you. Therefore take heed betime, and ceaſe your envie againſt the truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:166904:11"/>
               <head>And now to thoſe things you call our Principles.</head>
               <p>TO that you call the firſt Principle, <hi>viz. Not to ſalute any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> I anſwer, You falſely accuſe us in this as in other things, for the ſalutations of the Saints we owne and practice; It is your Heatheniſh cuſtomes you uſe by the way in taking the holy name of God into your mouthes in vaine, which God hath forbidden: and this we deny, and witneſſe againſt, that all might feare to pollute the dreadfull and glorious name of God. And now, let all that feare the name of God judge by what ſpirit you are guided who are not aſhamed to Preach and Print againſt us for this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nay, you are not aſhamed to wreſt the words of Chriſt, to contradict his owne commands, and the commands of God; as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 47. where he is exhorted to love, without reſpect of perſons, ſaying, <hi>If you love them that love you, that is no more but as the Publicans, and the Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen:</hi> and likewiſe in the ſalutation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>If ye ſalute your brethren onely,</hi> that is, as the Publican and Heathen practice: but here is no expreſſe command for ſalutation by the way, but a warning of the partiality of the Heatheniſh practiſe, as it is now practiſed with you, who will ſalute thoſe you love, and are rich in the world and to them you will bow and doe worſhip; but for the poore, and ſuch as you hate, theſe you paſſe by; and herein you ſhew your ſelves to be in the ſame nature with the Heathen, whoſe partiality Chriſt reproves and whoſe practiſes we deny. And whereas you alledge thoſe whom Chriſt ſent forth, who were to ſalute the houſe into which they entered; What is this to your high<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>way ſalutation? for they were to enquire what houſe was worthy, before they entered, or ſaluted; and they that had the Sonne of peace in them, was to ſpeake peace to that houſe; but if the Sonne of Peace was not there, their peace was to returne to them againe: Now neither this, nor the Apoſtles commanding the Saints to ſalute one another, doth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:166904:11"/>
warrant your Heatheniſh high-way cuſtomes, and taking the name of God in vain. And whereas you ſay, If we obſerve the command of not ſaluting by the way, then we ſhould alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to weare ſhooes. I anſwer, What we doe, is not from the command that was to others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor herein doe we walke by Tradition, but from command of the ſame power, by which we are ſent forth; and if we were commanded to forbeare wearing ſhooes, as well as we are commanded to deny your Heatheniſh cuſtomes and covetous practiſes, in not taking care for food and rayment, we ſhould be made willing to obey, as ſome have done who have been commanded to goe bare-foot, and ſome who have been commanded to goe naked (which you who know no particular commands from God, but walke by tradition in your owne wills, doing what you like, and leaving what you will undone) doe ſcorne and reproach as evill; and whereas you ſay, that Chriſt commanded the contrary to his twelve Diſciples, it is falſe; becauſe he commanded to ſalute the houſe that was worthy, this was not to command them to ſalute by the way, neither doth the practice of the Saints in ſaluting one another, contradict this command of Chriſt; neither are the Saints to conforme to the practice or faſhion of any Country, but to the commands of Chriſt which leads out of all the cuſtomes in the world. And whereas you ſay, There being a cleare command to ſalute all; we deny it, it is falſe; for where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If ye ſalute as the Heathens doe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> it is no command to ſalute all, but a warning to them of their partiality.</p>
               <p>To that you call our ſecond Principle, <hi>viz. Not giving any outward t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ken of reverence to Magiſtrates, Parents, Maſters, or any other.</hi> I anſwer, Herein you falſely accuſe us, as becauſe we deny to bow downe and worſhip any creature, which God hath forbidden; Is this to deny any token of reverence? for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their juſt commands is their greateſt reverence; and this we owne and practice for conſcience ſake; both to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Parents, and Maſters; and herein we deny your ſlander as falſe: And whereas you goe about to prove it by the practice of others, in their bowing downe to the creature, and thereby to breake the commands of God, which ſaith, <hi>Ye ſhall not bow down<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and worſhip.</hi> And whereas you alledge <hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethren
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:166904:12"/>
bowing downe to him, <hi>Abraham, Abigail, David,</hi> and the like, their practice, is no rule for us to breake the command of God, though they were good men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no more, then the practice of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> which ſwore <hi>by the life of Pbaraoh,</hi> is a warrant to us to ſweare, though he was a good man; or the practice of <hi>David</hi> in ſeiguing himſelfe mad, before <hi>Akiſh</hi> the King of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines, ſhould be made a warrant for us to fayne our ſelves mad, to avoyd your perſecution: Nor <hi>Iacob</hi> bowing before <hi>Eſau;</hi> for the Scripture ſaith. <hi>A righteous man falling downe before the wicked, is as a troubled Fountaine, and a corrupt ſpring.</hi> Pro. 25. 26.</p>
               <p>And whereas you charge us, that we ſay,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Is it not ſtrange theſe Prieſts in the 34 pag. of their Booke ſhall ſay, What is the power without the perſons? Government with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Governors but a meer fancy? and revile honouring the power, without reſpecting the Perſons. When in this Nation all obey and act by a Power in the name of the</hi> Keepers <hi>of the Liberties of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c. when there is no ſuch Perſons. Is the Government of this Nation but a fancy? And is it not high treaſon to ſubver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> them.?</hi> A. P.</note> 
                  <hi>We honour the Power, and not the Perſons.</hi> I anſwer, God is no reſpecter of Perſons, and you that would take the honour from the power which is of God, and would give it to mens perſons, would rob God of his honour, and are enemies to the Faith of Chriſt, who reſpects no ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> perſon, but ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> How can you beleeve that ſeek honour one of another; and would charge this to let in treaſon or diſobedience to Authority. I anſwer, Where did ever any who did reverence the power which was of God, doe any violence to the Perſon of any, into whoſe hands God had committed it, though they have been ſent by the Lord faithfully, to declare againſt the unjuſt practiſes of ſuch Governors, who have uſed their power contrary to the end for which God committed it into their hands; but this you caſt upon us to make us odions to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the earth, that they may take part with you in perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of us; but we ſtand in the power of the Lord, who will cleare our innocency, and diſtinguiſh betweene them who ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and obey his power in the truth, and them that have mens perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage, for ſelfe ends; for ſuch admire the perſons of men no longer then then ſerve for their own ends, as it is apparant at this day.</p>
               <p>To that you call the third Principle, <hi>viz. That no Man muſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:166904:12"/>
have the title of Maſter.</hi> I anſwer, Here, as in other things, you would bring the practice of men in the old Teſtament, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anull the expreſſe commands of Chriſt in the New, and ſo would ſet the Old Covenant againſt the New, and would bring Scriptures againſt Chriſt; and here you ſhew your ſelves to be of the Serpents brood, who have alwayes wreſted the words of God againſt himſelfe, and to make voyd his commands; and let all who feare the Lord judge, if you be worthy to be called the Miniſters of Chriſt, who are not afraid to contend againſt his expreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> commands, becauſe it ſtrikes at your pride<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and would make people beleeve, that pride in you is not as much hated by Chriſt, as it was in the Phariſees, when you are ſound in the ſame generation, in the ſame pride, and affecting to your ſelves the ſame Titles, which they that are guided by the ſame ſpirit of Chriſt, ſee, and witneſſe againſt in whomſoever it is now, as was then.</p>
               <p>Now for the fourth perticular, which you call<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Charges againſt your ſelves and are ſo againſt all that are found in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, That they love the high places of the Synagogues. 2. That they weare long Robes. 3. That they ſtand Praying in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues. 4 That they Preach for hire, To which I may ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a great ſort more, which are the markes which Chriſt and his Apoſtles did give, whereby to know the falſe Teachers then, and cryed woe againſt them, warning all to take h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed of them, in which practiſes, whoſoever are found now, are witneſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by the ſame ſpirit, as was then; as to lay heavy barthens upon the people; to ſay, and not to doe; to be proud, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, heady, high-minded, deſpiſers of them that are good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> falſe accuſars, ſpeaking evill of the things they know not having a Forme of godlineſſe, but denying the power thereof; having hearts exerciſed with covetous practiſes that cannot ceaſe from ſinne, that through covetouſneſſe, make merchandize of the people, who run greedily after the wayes of <hi>Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am,</hi> who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſſe; and in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> in envy; who pretend to be ſheep, but raven and devoure like Wolves. Now, ſaith Chriſt and his Apoſtles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuch ſhall come, but by their fruits yee ſhall know them; and they that then were gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ded by the eternall ſpirit of God, did know them, judge of them, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:166904:13"/>
warne of them by theſe fruits; and though you now, in who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe fruits are found, would caſt them upon your fore-fathers, the Scribes and Phariſees, thereby keeping people looking at that ſin in them, but hiding and covering it in your ſelves; yet they that are guided by the ſame eternall ſpirit now, ſee you to be in the ſame generation, to bring forth the ſame fruits, and doe judge you, and warne of you now, as they did then; and it is no new thing for the deceipt, to cry out of their fore-fathers for the ſame ſins, wherein they are found themſelves, as the Scribes and Phariſees builded the Sepulchres of the Prophets, and cryed out of their Fathers for Killing them, but being blinde, could not ſee themſelves worſe then their fore-fathers, who were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting to ſlay the Heire; ſo yee, make a trade of crying out of the pride of the Phariſees, and their being called Maſters, and their loving greeting in the Markets, and the higheſt places, and being hirelings, and perſecuting Chriſt and the Saints, rayſing lyes, and ſeeking falſe witneſſe againſt him, ſtirring up the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and the rude people, thereby to take away his life, becauſe he witneſſed againſt their ungodly practiſes; and thus you make a trade of crying out againſt them b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t are found in the very ſame things by thoſe who are guided by the ſame ſpirit; yet being blinde, you will not owne them in your ſelves; but Chriſt hath left no other rule without as to know ſuch, but by their fruits. Therefore let all who profeſſe the name of Chriſt, ſo judge, that where theſe fruits are found, not to caſt them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the generations paſt, but to avoyd them now. And, ſaith the Apoſtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from ſuch tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e away: And it is in vaine for you by your ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilty to wreſt and twine the Scriptures to cleare your ſelves of theſe things, when ye are found in them by the Lord, and all who are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> guided by his ſpirit; and in pleading for your hire, ye ſay, you freely caſt your ſelves upon the Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maintenance; herein we witneſſe againſt you, Where in the Goſhel had ever any a ſet maintenance, Tythe, or augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or by any agreement from the people, or by any power of the Magiſtracy, or by any ſuites at the Law, or any other chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lange, but freely? but ye that goe upon any of theſe accompts, or any other accompt, but freely, doe not caſt your ſelves upon the Goſpel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> maintenance; neither doe all theſe Scriptures you
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:166904:13"/>
alledge, or the practice of the Apoſtles, make any thing to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant your way of maintenance, but doe witneſſe againſt you; as is plaine to whomſoever doth looke with a ſingle eye into the Apoſtles practiſes, and into yours: And whereas yee ſay, We charge you with ſtealing the Word from your neighbours; and this you would evade by Chriſt and the Apoſtles quoting the Scriptures, which we doe not deny: But which of all the true Prophets, Chriſt, or his Apoſtles, did take the words that were ſpoken to another, and adde to them their owne inventions and braine ſtudy, and come amongſt people, and ſay, Heare the Word of the Lord, when the Lord had not ſpoken to them? but the ſalſe Prophets did ſo; and, ſaith the Lord, <hi>I am againſt them that ſteale my Word from their Neighbours, and ſay, The Lord ſaith, when I have not ſpoken to them;</hi> and ye doing the ſame things, are diſcovered by the ſame ſpirit. And whereas yee pleade againſt our uſing the Scripture phraſe, in <hi>thouing</hi> eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y particular we ſpeake to, and pleading againſt us the cuſtomes of the Nation, here yee ſhew your ſelves to be guided by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſpirit to Chriſt, who leades his out of all the cuſtomes of the world, and the Nations, and thereby they are knowne not to be of the world; and yee who are Miniſters of the Letter, and diſpute againſt the language of it, which none of Gods ever denyed or diſputed againſt; out of your enmity to the truth, yee pleade againſt what yee profeſſe, and are miniſters of, and all this ye doe to maintain the confuſed language, which all they who are redeemed out of the fall, are reſtored to a pure Language. Now as touching your conſideration of our practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: and firſt concerning <hi>Quaking and trembling;</hi> to which yee adde, <hi>grovelling upon the ground, and foaming at the mouth,</hi> which are lyes and ſlanders of your owne inventing: but for <hi>quaking and trembling</hi> we owne it, as that which the Lord hath ſaid ſhall come upon all fleſh, and which the Saints have wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed through the Scripture; and if we ſhould deny them, we ſhould deny the holy men of God, as <hi>Moſes, Iſaac, David, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bakkuk<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Daniel, Ezekiel, Ieremiah, Paul,</hi> and many other of the deare ſervants of God, and ſhew our ſelves to be ſtrangers to that condition by which they came to know the Lord, as yee doe, who revile and reproach it. And whereas you tell of three
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:166904:14"/>
ſorts of trembling in the Scripture, but know them not within your ſelves, ye are not to be regarded, nor what ye ſpeake by heare-ſay, who are ſcorners of their conditions which ye reade in Scripture; neither doe ye know from what they proceed, but judge of them in your owne imagination, and in this, as in other things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> contend againſt what is witneſſed in Scripture, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> up all the lyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſlanders, and weakeneſſe of any to caſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the truth and the Saints condition. And whereas ye ſay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> call theſe <hi>quakings</hi> our great <hi>perfection;</hi> that is falſe, and a lying ſlander, like the reſt; our <hi>perfection</hi> ſtands not in any outward things, but in the good and perfect gift which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now of our ſecond practice, which ye call <hi>Rayling.</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, If they ſpeake of ye the things that are true, and in which you live, will ye call the truth, <hi>Rayling,</hi> though it come in an unwelcome language to the diſobedient natures? Was it <hi>rayling</hi> in Chriſt, to call them, <hi>The children of the Devill, who brought forth the workes of the Devill;</hi> or to call them <hi>Serpents, and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> who ſought by their ſubtilty to devoure the ſimple? Or to call <hi>Herod</hi> a <hi>Fox,</hi> who was a King; or for the Apoſtles and Saints to call them <hi>Dogs, and Swine,</hi> who loved their ſins and filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and could not be kept from returning into it againe. For they who did ſtand in the light of the ſpirit of God, did diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the contrary ſpirit, which did act ſeverall wayes in the men of the world, and ſome they ſaw to be <hi>Doggs,</hi> ſome <hi>Wolves,</hi> ſome <hi>bryars and thornes,</hi> ſome <hi>high-Mountains,</hi> ſome <hi>fat Bulls,</hi> which did compaſſe the innocent about to devoure them, ſome <hi>Witches,</hi> who bewitched the Saints from the guiding of the ſpirit to carnall things: Now, will you call theſe <hi>Raylers,</hi> becauſe they ſpeak the truth upon the ſeverall actings of the ſpirit of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill where it was? But they were the ſervants of the Lord, and were meeke, and gentle, and patient towards all men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even ſo theſe ſervants of the Lord now, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they ſpeake the truth as things are found in ye, revealed unto them by the ſame ſpirit, are no <hi>raylers,</hi> but are meeke, gentle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and patient; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, they muſt doe the Meſſage of the Lord faithfully.</p>
               <p>Now to the third practice, <hi>They pretending, upon all occaſions to be ſent by Commiſſion from God, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall inſtance in ſome caſes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:166904:14"/>
following <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> I anſwer, the Meſſages that God have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his ſervants on, have been ſtrange to the world, neit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> could the world, who knew not the voyce of the Lord, ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them, but have been counted mad men, mad fellows, fooles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> with new Wine, and ſuch like; Yet I ſhall not here juſtifie every one, who ſaith, he is ſent of the Lord, for many lying ſpirits are gone out into the world; but woe unto him that runneth, and is not ſent, and belyeth the Lord, when he hath not ſpoken unto him: but as for your particuler char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> particular perſons, I ſhall ſay little, as not knowing the things in particuler; but finding your Booke ſtuſt with lyes and untruths<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> gives me cauſe to beleeve, that many of theſe are like the reſt: Onely, this is plaine Scripture, That the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the Lord which he ſends his people on, are fooliſhnes to the wiſedom of the world, and ſo they are to ye; and though ye would appoint them their place, and manner, and time, yet it is neither in your wills, nor theirs, but in the will of God which if any out of feare or favour doe not obey, they ſhall ſuffer for it. And whereas ye declare of comming of ſome of us to <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> this I witneſſe to be true, as in the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſence of God,<note place="margin">E. B.</note> that our Call was from God, and our Commiſſion was from him, and therefore did ſuffer perſecution by you, and by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates; but as for our declaring our Meſſage before the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, my Brother and Siſter were interrupted by ſome of you in their declaring. But that they who were before the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates were invited to go to any of your houſes to ſpeak, is falſe; and here <hi>W. C.</hi> is a falſe witneſſe. And whereas ye accuſe us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>For caſting off the Word of God.</hi> I anſwer, It is falſe, for the Word of God we owne, and obey, for which we are ſcorned, and ſuffers reproach by ye. For your accuſing <hi>George Fox</hi> for curſing Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Fetherſton,</hi> as ye call him, I my ſelfe was in preſence, when <hi>Fetherſton</hi> confeſſed: that the words which <hi>George Fox</hi> ſpoke was Scripture. And for your ſlander ye caſt upon <hi>Chriſtopher At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſon,</hi> and a Woman, for their familiarity; and to make a ground for your ſlander, ye ſay (<hi>to ſay no more</hi>) but why, to ſay no more? if ye know more, why doe you not ſpeake the truth, but ſlander in ſecret? And here you falſe accuſer, thou and thy witneſſe ſhall both be taken alive, and caſt into the Pit,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:166904:15"/>
who hath deceived the people by thy falſe lyes and ſlanders; thou charges me with my immodeſt familiarity with a Woman of<note place="margin">C. A.</note> my way; and to colour thy deceit, thou ſayſt, (<hi>to ſay no more</hi>) thou falſe accuſer of the Saints of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I challenge thee, and companion, to prove what you have ſpoken againſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and not onely ſo, but againſt all the Church of God, who doth ſuffer by you, who live in pride<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Dives</hi>-like. And as for thee <hi>W. C.</hi> thou art made knowne to be of that generation which put the Saints to death; but the Lord ſhall pleade with thee, and give thee thy portion in utter darkeneſſe for ever. As for <hi>Wallas</hi> your witneſſe herein, whom yee call a godly Miniſter, he ſaid in the hearing of many people, That it was no murther in him to murther <hi>Chriſtopher Atkinſon,</hi> and the reſt of the Priſoners at <hi>Kendall,</hi> being neere twenty; now, how this mans teſtimony may be truſted, or that he would keep any thing backe that might adde to the ſlander, any honeſt man may judge, for the murtherer and the lyar are one, and he that makes no conſcience of the one, makes none of the other: But here, as in the reſt of your Book, ye take up things from ſuch hands, and adde to them your owne inventions, to make us vile in the ſight of the people. And for any going naked, or being otherwiſe made ſignes and wonders to yee, which ye charge as a great thing againſt us, yee being ignorant of the power of God; by which theſe men are acted, any wiſe man may know theſe doe it not according to their owne wills, but in obedience unto God, which commands, ſome have denyed to obey, for which, the heavy judgements of God have been layd upon them, from which they could not be freed, till they were made obedient, as is well knowne in <hi>Kendall.</hi> And now to your reaſons, why yee call us <hi>Phariſets, Monkes and Fryars,</hi> or any thing to render us moſt odious to all people, which is no ſtrange thing for us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from that ſeed, from whence it coms, neither doth is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us, that the Scripture be fulfilled, which ſaith, <hi>As they have done unto me, ſo will they doe unto you;</hi> neither is the ſervant greater then his Lord; therefore doe we rejoyce therein, as a ſure teſtimony that God hath called us from among you, and we are not of you, neither can you love us, therefore we looke for no other at your hands; and though, as concerning ourſelves, we
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:166904:15"/>
ſhould be ſilent, yet for the truths ſake, I ſhall ſpeake a few words, to lay open your owne falſe ſlanders in ſome of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, wherein ye compare us to <hi>Phariſees, Monkes and Fryars.</hi> And firſt ye ſay, <hi>The Phariſees did ſeperate themſelves from the reſt of the people, upon a conceit of their owne holineſſe.</hi> I anſwer, Selfe we deny, and all that ſeperates themſelves by the power of ſelfe, for there ye are; but we are ſeperated by the light of Chriſt, whereby we are called out of the world, and ſet free from all conceits of our owne holineſſe; and it is no other holineſſe we owne, but the holineſſe of God, witneſſing againſt all unholy practiſes of the world; neither doe we owne any to be Saints, who walke in unholineſſe; and here we have the practice of all the Saints in Scripture to witneſſe for us, who were ſeperated by the ſame light out of all the unholy practiſes of the World, who were made the righteouſneſſe of God in Chriſt, and denyed themſelves and ſelfe-righteouſneſſe: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your falſe accuſation we deny.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For your accuſing us to be Phariſees, <hi>For ſtanding in our owne Knowledge, and ſaying, Theſe are accurſed who know not the Law.</hi> I anſwer, This is your owne, who ſtand ſo much in your owne Knowledge, that would have all to come to ye to be taught; but our owne Knowledge we deny, and waite onely for the Knowledge of God revealed to us in Jeſus Chriſt. And for calling <hi>Devills and mad-men,</hi> which ye caſt upon us, that is your owne language. And whereas ye ſay, <hi>We judge the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full uſe of meats and drinkes,</hi> that is falſe; we ſpeake againſt your glutteny and drunkenneſſe, and exceſſe, which all the holy men of God have ſpoken againſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whereas ye accuſe us, <hi>For ſhutting up the Kingdome of Heaven againſt men,</hi> Mat. 23. 13. I anſwer, Thoſe whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaks on there, were ſuch as were hypocrites, which ſaid and did not, which Preached to others that which they did not practice themſelves: and here<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let all judge if this be not your owne, which ye would caſt upon us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Ye charge us, <hi>With compaſſing Sea and Land to make one Proſelite, and when he is made, he is two-fold more the Childe of Hell then he was.</hi> I anſwer, Our endeavours is to call people out of their ſins, not in ſhews, but in reality, as many will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:166904:16"/>
with us; but your pleading is to perſwade people, that they muſt never overcome their ſins,. Now vvho makes Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites the children of Hell, but they that keep them in the works of the Devill; and they that Preach ſuch Doctrine, are they that poyſon the hearts: but to turne from ſin unto God, is to purifie, and not to poyſon.</p>
               <p n="5">5. You charge us, <hi>With Tything Mint and Anniſe, but negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the weightier matters of the Law.</hi> And ye ſay, <hi>We lay all the weight upon triviall obſervances of Hats, Thou, Clothes, &amp;c. but doe wholly neglect the Myſteries of Faith, Righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and Ordinances of the Goſpel.</hi> I anſwer, For Tything, that is your owne, and ye contend for it, neither dare we call any thing triviall that the Lord requires of us, though vve lay not the vveight upon theſe things. And for the neglecting the Myſtery of Faith, and the Righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, that is falſe, for the Myſtery of Faith is held in a pure Conſcience, and that vve owne, and preſſe every one to practice. And the Righteouſneſſe of Chriſt vve owne, and the Ordinances of the Goſpel vvhich is Chriſt, vve owne; onely your invention and tradition, vvhich was never Ordayned by Chriſt, we deny.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Ye charge us, <hi>With making cleane the out-ſide of the Cup, being whited Sepulchres, outwardly appearing beautifull to men, but within full of hypocriſie and iniquity.</hi> I anſwer, Now whether this belong to us, who witneſſe our light, and righteouſneſſe within, vvhich is the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt in ſpirit; or to ye, vvho have your light and righteouſneſſe vvithout, in your Formes, but vvithin are full of pride, covetouſneſſe, lying, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, and ſuch like filthy practiſes, vvhich vve deny; now whom this charge vvill fall upon, let the truth judge. And whereas ye ſay, <hi>We doe our works to be ſeen of men,</hi> becauſe the Lord ſends ſome of us into your Idols Temples, Streets, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets. I anſwer, Was it not the practice of the Apoſtles to goe into the Synagogues and Market places, vvhere the people vvas, to declare their Meſſage they had from the Lord, and yet they did it not to be ſeen of men. And whereas ye ſay, <hi>We pray not at all, but are the Heathen that knowes not God, and the Family that calls not on his name.</hi> I anſwer, Thoſe vvho know our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, ſhall vvitneſſe againſt your falſe accuſation: and for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:166904:16"/>
Heingathen, that is your owne, vvho exerciſe authority over your owne hearers, and pleade for your Heatheniſh cuſtomes, vvhereby it appears ye know not God, And vvhereas ye charge us <hi>with crying up our own holineſſe, and our ſelves as extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prophets, Rabbies, and Doctors.</hi> I anſwer, It is falſe, for it is Chriſts holineſſe vve owne, and Chriſt the everlaſting Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and Prieſt, vve owne, vvhereby vve deny ye vvho goe under the namy of Rabbies and Doctors. And vvhereas ye charge us, <hi>with neglect of Apparell, Faſting, and ſeperating from the world.</hi> I anſwer, What Apparell doe vve neglect, ſaving the pride and vanity vvhich you live in, and vve are made to vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt, for vvhich you hate us: And for Faſting, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perating from the World, for ſhame doe not profeſſe your ſelves to be Chriſtians, vvhile you caſt the commands of Chriſt, and practice of the Saints upon us, in ſcorne and deriſion. Did not Chriſt command to forſake the World? and vvas not the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in Faſting often? but you ſhew your ſelves not to be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by that ſpirit, but envie them vvho are: And ye that ſcorne Viſions and Revelations, are ignorant of that, by vvhich the Saints came to know God, for no man knowes God, but by Revelation. Whereas you charge us <hi>with laying the weight of our juſtification upon outward obſervances.</hi> I anſwer, It is falſe, for the vveight of our juſtification is layd upon Chriſt, in us the hope of glory. Whereas ye ſay, <hi>Ye have not been injurious to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, in calling us Papiſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Monkes and Fryars.</hi> I anſwer, The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury vvill be to your ſelves, for vve reſt in patience, vvhile vve ſee the Scripture fulfilled, vvhich ſaith, <hi>They ſhall caſt out your names as evill, and ſhall ſpeake all manner of evill of ye falſely, for my names ſake;</hi> which we beare with patience, as owning it to be our portion from that Generation. And now let every honeſt heart who reades theſe two Books, and knoweth our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and ſeeth the multitude of lyes and ſlanders caſt upon us, judge, whether ye have done this from an honeſt principle, and the eſtabliſhing of the Faith, or with an intent to ſlander us, and make the truth odious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe we have been brought forth as witneſſes againſt your unrighteous practiſes: and we leave it unto the righteous Judge, who is the ſearcher of all hearts, to cleare the innocent in his ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e time and will, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:166904:17"/>
to find out the guilty and diſcover him, that ſimple ſoules may be no longer deceived through falſe gloſſes, and the ſubtilty of craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty men of corrupt minds, for their owne ends, which we know is the worke of the Lord that he is about, and therefore with patience we waite his time, into whoſe hands and keeping we commit our ſelves, and all the faithfull of the Lord, who is a ſure refuge to the truth. To whom be all glory and holy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from all that know him, for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now a word to ye five who have ſubſcribed this Booke, that yee may ſee by what ſpirit yee are carryed on to utter ſo many untruths and falſe reports, taken up by heare-ſay, without any ground at all; and divers things out of Books, which you cannot be ignorant, how ye have on purpoſe wreſted to ſlander withall, that if there be any Principle of honeſty in any of you, yee may repent before the Lord, and that it may not be layd to your charge at the great day, when all hearts ſhall be layd open. But in the meane time, this I know, that what ye have intended againſt the truth, and to keep off the ſimple from owning of it, ſhall by the wiſedome of God ſo lay open your deceit and envy, that it ſhall advance the truth, in the ſight of every ſimple heart; which if the truth may but be exalted, and my Father thereby honoured, it is nothing to me, how vile I ſeeme before men; and therefore in peace I reſt, giving my ſelfe to the will of God, and what I have Written, to be judged by all the Children of the light, which is not my owne, but his, from whom I have received it, who will defend it againſt all the wilde Beaſts of the World, and whom he will, ſhall profit by it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And ſo I reſt, a Servant of the Truth, knowne to the World be the Name of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>James Nayler.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:166904:17"/>
            <head>A Word to all thoſe who live after their own wills, that they may be Witneſſes againſt themſelves, that they are Perſecuters, and may reade their Cloud of Witneſſes, who ever Perſecuted the Righteous Seed, who is our Cloud of Witneſſes.</head>
            <p>ALl People take warning, now while you have time prize it, for the mighty day of the Lord is comming; Woe uoto you that are pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and high minded, you will be as ſtubble before the fire; howle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> woe and miſery, your down fall day is comming, weep and howle, ye mighty men, ye lofty ones, ye rebelliou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cones, the ſword of the Lord is drawne, it is forbiſhed and made fit for the ſlaughter, the loftineſſe of man ſhall be brought low<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> caſt off your hoods, and your rings, your filkes and your proud attire; g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ird you with ſaekdoath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> prepare to meet the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the trumpet of the Lord is ſounded, his ſword ſhall be made fat with ſlaughter, and there ſhall be no peace to the wicked; the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet ſhall be ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> into the lake of fire: great <hi>Babylon</hi> is come into remembrance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, ſtrong is the Lord that jungeth her, ſhe muſt have double for all her ſins, ſhe muſt drink of the Cup of fury and indignation from the hand of the Lord, for ſhe hath made all Nations drunke with the Wine of her Fornication, even all the Kings and great men of the Earth is <hi>drunke</hi> with the cup of Whoredome; myſtery, <hi>Babylon</hi> the mother of Herlots, hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Nations, and ſhe muſt be caſt upon the bed of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; howle ye merchants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who through covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>makes</hi> merchandiſe of ſoules: howle <hi>ye proud Prieſts of Newcaſtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> who ſet your neſts on high<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>takes</hi> part with the Dragon in the warr againſt the Lambe, and deceives the ſimple
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:166904:18"/>
by your ſubtilties; the Lord is comming to lay you open, and to gather his ſheep from your mouthes and you ſhall be taken with the Whore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with whom you have committed Fornication, and ſhall be partakers of her plagues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the wrath of the Lord is <hi>kindled</hi> againſt you, and your deſtruction is at hand, the mouth of the Lord hath <hi>ſpoken</hi> it; therefore, come out from among them, my people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and be ye ſeperated, and I will receive you, ſaith the Lord: for now am I riſen to redeem Syon with judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to render vengeance upon her oppreſſors: Heare the Word of the Lord, ye Inhabitants of the Land O how is the Land full of ſwearers, and lyars drunkards and raylers, ſcoffers and ſcornets? O how full is the ſtreets of prophane perſons, <hi>Eſau like?</hi> How full is the ſtreets of proud ones, who exalts themſelves above all that is called god. Tremble, tremble ye lofty ones, who takes that to your ſelves, which belongs to God; for he hath ſayd, <hi>You ſhall not bow downe nor worſhip any creaſure:</hi> And you who pretend juſtice, who ſhould judge without reſpect of perſons, you are found tranſgreſſors of the pure Law of God, which reſpects no mans perſon: and the Lord is againſt you who are tranſgreſſors of his pure Law, for he that reſpects per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons commits ſin, and the Lord will in no wiſe acquit the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the Lord is againſt you, who in ſtead of exec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon them who live in wickedneſſe, which your ſtreets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with, you draw your ſword to puniſh them, and to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon them who are ſent of the Lord to cry againſt theſe abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; you chuſe <hi>Barraba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and Crucifie <hi>Jeſus;</hi> you priſon the Saints of the moſt high God for ſpeaking the Word of the Lord, which you ſhall eternally witneſſe, whether you will heare or forbeare the word of the Lord ſhall ſtand, and muſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne in vaine. Weep and howle for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon you, the whirle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> winde of the Lord is gone forth, and it will fall heavy upon the head of the wicked. Ah woe is me, my heart within me is broken, to ſee the prophaneſſe of Prieſts and people. <hi>Ah,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will caſe me of mine adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and avenge me of mine enemies.</hi> O returne returne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the day of your viſitation; confeſſe and forſake your ſins, that you may finde mercy, for if you goe on in the broad way, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ads to deſtruction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and there are all the proud Prieſts acting in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:166904:18"/>
the generation, which ever perſecuted the righteous ſeed; we have a cloud of witneſſes which was perſecuted of your genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was put in the ſtockes, and in the dungeon, for <hi>ſpeaking the Word of the Lord. Daniel</hi> was caſt into the Lyons den, becauſe he would not bow to the Image which the King had ſet up. <hi>Mord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ai</hi> was hated, and all the ſeed of the Jews, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would not bow to proud <hi>Hammon.</hi> The Apoſtles was put in the <hi>ſtockes</hi> and in the common Priſon, <hi>for ſpeaking</hi> in the name of Jeſus: they were hayled out of the Synagogues, and carried before Rulers, for bearing witneſſe to the ſubſtance. <hi>Steven</hi> was ſtoned to death by an uncircumciſed and ſtiffe-necked people. All the holy men of God, of whom the world was not worthy, ſome of them were ſtoned, ſome ſawne aſunder, others put to cruell death; and the Saints had tryalls of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tuell mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſcourgings; yea, of bonds and impriſonments; and he who was the Heyre<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſubſtance of Law and Prophets, bleſſed for ever he was called a blaſphemer, and mocked, and put to death by the high Prieſts, Scribes and Elders of the people; and all thoſe who was choſen out of the world, was perſecuted and hated, becauſe they were not of the world: theſe are our cloud of witneſſes, glory to our God for evermore, who hath counted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s worthy to ſuffer for his name, the reproach for Chriſt is greater riches then the treaſures of Egypt; Prayſes, prayſes to our God fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> evermore: weep and howle ye perſecuters ye lyers, ye ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, for upon your generation ſhall all the righteous blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed be required, your cloud of witneſſes was perſecuters, and you fill up the meaſure of your Fathers iniquity. Proud <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſought to <hi>ſlay Mordecai,</hi> becauſe he did not bow to him, according to the Kings commandement, for he had received the Law from God, which ſeed will not bow to the Devill, the chiefe Prieſt, who were called of men Maſter, and had the chiefeſt place in the Aſſemblies, and ſtood praying, and went in long Robes, theſe called Chriſt a Blaſphemer; the chiefe Prieſts fought falſe witneſſe againſt Chriſt in which generation are theſe five proud Prieſts, who are found falſe witneſſes, calling truth, error; woe unto them, as they have been witneſſes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the Lord in their Words and Writings ſo ſhall they be partakers together of the cup of fury from the hand of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:166904:19"/>
Lord; for they act as their Fore-fathers did, the chiefe Prieſts gave large money to the ſouldiers to belye Chriſt, that they might ſay his Diſciples ſtole him away; the chiefe Prieſts gave money to <hi>Judas</hi> to betray Chriſt, and confeſſed, It was the price of blood. The Chiefe Prieſts ſought to Kill <hi>Lazarus,</hi> whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> had rayſed from the dead, becauſe many through him did beleeve. The chiefe Prieſts tooke councell againſt Chriſt, how they might take him by ſubtilty, and Kill him. The Chiefe Prieſts put the Apoſtles in the common priſon. The Prieſt <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah</hi> bad the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> depart, and Propheſie no more at the Kings Chapell, nor the Kings Court; and told the King, The Prophet of the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lord had conſpired againſt him, and that the Land was not able to beare all his Words, <hi>Ames</hi> 7. The Chiefe Prieſts was the greateſt enemies to Jeſus Chriſt; and <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilat</hi> was made friends at his death. Theſe are our Cloude of Witneſſes, and ye are the ſame now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Prieſt and People, where Chriſt is made manifeſt; for the ſame Chriſt is perſecuted now, as was then, by them who have the letter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the forme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as they had then: Where did you ever teade that Chriſt, or the Saints perſecuted or priſoned any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but you fill up the meaſure of your Fathers iniquity, and be you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> witneſſes againſt your ſelves, that you are in the curſed generation which Chriſt cryed woe unto? How can ye eſcape the damnation of Hell? The Lord our God is comming in power, to render vengeance upon your heads; ye blinde guides, and proud hypocrites<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ye perſecuters of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſeed, your fruits make you manifeſt to be the ſeed of evil doers; the <hi>Lord</hi> is comming to gather his people from your mouthes, and to render vengeance upon you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold you. Rejoyce ye righteous ones, for Syons deliverance is at hand, Prayſes to our God for evermore. Written from the ſpirit of the <hi>Lord,</hi> by a Servant of the <hi>Lrrd,</hi> whom the world calls a <hi>Quaker,</hi> whoſe name in the Fleſh is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Andland.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
